Guide to the Duer family papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Duer family Papers,
1784-1937.
Duer family.
2.515 linear feet (7 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY.
MS#0369
4078716
The Duer Family papers include correspondence, diaries, genealogical manuscripts and notes, miscellaneous poetry, and early photographs, daguerreotypes, tintypes, engravings, and illustrations (the Duer coat of arms). The collection depicts aspects of social customs in Old New York, patriotism, and life abroad.
Biographical Note
The Duer Family was one of the founding families of New York City. Prior to moving to New York from England, the Duer Family had purchased tracts of land on the Hudson River near Albany. The area, known as Fort Miller, served as their first residence and as the site of their early financial ventures. By 1776 the Duer family had built a successful mercantile business based primarily on lumber production.
The Duer family patriarch, William Duer (March 18, 1743-May 7, 1799), was an American lawyer, developer, and speculator who lived in New York City. A Federalist, he had served in the Continental Congress and the convention that framed the New York Constitution. In 1778, he signed the United States Articles of Confederation. Duer was married to Katherine "Kitty" Alexander, the daughter of the Revolutionary War General William Alexander (Lord Stirling), and together they had three sons: William Alexander, Alexander and John.
William Alexander Duer (1780-1858) son of William Duer, was an American lawyer, jurist, educator, member of the New York State Assembly (1816), and one of the first eight New York State Circuit Courts judges appointed (1823). He served as the President of Columbia College (now Columbia University) from 1829 to 1842.
William Alexander and Hannah Denning Duer (1782-1862) had four children: Henrietta Amlie, Frances Maria, Catherine Theodora, and William Denning. The writings and correspondence of William Alexander, Hannah Maria Denning Duer, and their daughter Frances Maria Duer Hoyt are featured throughout this collection.
Scope and Content
The Duer Family Papers consists primarily of correspondence, documents, and books pertaining to the Duer Family as well as tintypes, daguerreotypes, photographs and illustrations. Also included in the collection are the diaries of Frances Maria Duer Hoyt's travels in Europe from 1864 to 1894, and the diaries of Hannah Maria Denning Duers from 1838 to 1862.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series.
I. Correspondence and Manuscripts.
II. Photographs and Illustrations.
III. Books.
Subjects
Columbia College (New York, N.Y.)--Presidents.; Alexander, William, 1726-1783.; Bridgen, Anna; Duer, Caroline, 1865-1956.; Duer, Hannah Maria Denning.; Duer, William, 1747-1799; Duer, William Alexander, 1780-1858.; Hoyt, Frances Maria Duer; Miller, Alice Duer, 1874-1942.; Van Rensselaer, John King, Mrs., 1848-1925.; Van Rensselaer, Stephen, 1764-1839; France--Description and travel.; Italy--Description and travel.; Aristocracy (Social class)--New York (State)--New York--History--19th century.; Expatriation.; Families--New York; Patriotism--United States.; United States--Continental Congress--Members; Wealth--Social Aspects--New York (State)--New York--History--19th century; Women--Diaries.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Miller, Alice Duer Gift 1937
Benjamin, Mary Gift 1956
Miller, Denning Gift 1981
Granat, Henry Gift 1986
The Duer family papers were assembled by Caroline King Duer (1865-1956), Alice Duer Miller (1874-1942, Barnard College A.B., 1899), and May King Van Rensselaer (1848-1925).
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Alice Duer Miller Papers, Barnard College Archives.
Duer Family Papers, Barnard College Archives.
Elizabeth Meads Duer Papers, Barnard College Archives.
Caroline King Duer Papers, Barnard College Archives.
"Reminiscences of Caroline King Duer," Oral History Research Office.
Selected Related Material-- Other Repositories
Papers of George Washington, University of Virgina.
Papers of William Duer, New-York Historical Society.
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1784-1937
  - B-D (Box 1)
    - Bridgen, Anna (Box 1)
    - Duer, Hannah Maria Denning (Mrs. William Alexander) (Box 1)
    - Duer, William (Box 1)
    - Duer, William Alexander (Box 1)
  - Hoyt, Frances Maria Duer (Mrs. Henry Sheaff) (Box 2)
  - K-V, and miscellany (Box 3)
    - King, James Gore (Box 3)
    - Miller, Alice Duer (Box 3)
    - Poor, Henry William (Box 3)
    - Swan, Jane P. (Box 3)
    - Van Rensselaer, May King (Box 3)
- Series II: Photographs and Illustrations
  - Duer Family Daguerrotypes (Box 4)
    These include images of Caroline King Duer, William Alexander Duer, Hibbard, John Meads, Orlando Meads, Elizabeth Wilson Meads (Mrs. Orlando), Orlando Meads, Jr., and the Meads Family.
  - Unidentified Duer Family Dauguerrotypes (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Engravings, and Coat of Arms Illustrations (Box 6)
- Series III. Books, 1847-1867
  - Duer, William A. The Life of William Alexander, Earl of Stirling. New York: Wiley & Putnam, 1847 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Duer, William A. A Course of Lectures on the Constitutional Jurisprudence of the United States delivered annually in Columbia College of New York. Boston: Little, Brown and Co., 1856 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Duer, William A. Reminiscences of an Old New Yorker. New York; W.L. Andrews, 1867 (Box 7, Folder 3)